<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-26T14:03:56+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ryan Blanchard</title><subtitle>Artificial Intelligence trends and concepts made easy.</subtitle><author><name>Ryan Blanchard PhD</name></author><entry><title type="html">Xfoil for Fixed Wing UAV / Human-Powered Aircraft Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/xfoil_wing_design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Xfoil for Fixed Wing UAV / Human-Powered Aircraft Design" /><published>2026-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2026-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/xfoil_wing_design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/xfoil_wing_design.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-xfoil-matters">Why XFOIL Matters</h2>

<p>Designing a wing always starts with the same uncomfortable gap:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can draw a beautiful airfoil shape — but how do you know what it <em>does</em> aerodynamically?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For conventional aircraft, that gap is often bridged with wind-tunnel data, empirical charts, or CFD. For <strong>small UAVs</strong> and <strong>human-powered aircraft</strong>, those options are either too expensive or too slow to iterate.</p>

<p>XFOIL, written in Fortran at MIT by Mark Drela <a href="https://web.mit.edu/drela/Public/web/xfoil/">mit.edu/drela/xfoil</a>, sits precisely in that gap. It provides a fast, physics-based way to go from <strong>geometry</strong> to <strong>aerodynamic coefficients</strong> — lift, drag, and moment — as a function of <strong>angle of attack</strong> and <strong>Reynolds number</strong>. That makes it an indispensable tool for early-stage wing design, especially when iteration speed matters.</p>

<p>For my pedal-powered aircraft project, XFOIL is the first link in the chain connecting a 2D airfoil sketch to a full 3D wing and, eventually, to a flyable machine. Paying the up front price for getting old Fortran to compile on Apple silicon with a series of python wrappers around it for automation has paid huge dividends for speeding up my analysis cycles.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-low-reynolds-number-reality">The Low Reynolds Number Reality</h2>

<p>One key reason XFOIL is so central to my workflow is that I operate in a very different aerodynamic regime than most airplanes.</p>

<p>The Reynolds number is defined as:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\mathrm{Re} = \frac{\rho U c}{\mu}
$$
</div>

<p>where:</p>
<ul>
  <li>$ \rho $ is air density</li>
  <li>$ U $ is freestream velocity</li>
  <li>$ c $ is the characteristic length (airfoil chord)</li>
  <li>$ \mu $ is dynamic viscosity</li>
</ul>

<p>Large transport aircraft operate at Reynolds numbers on the order of $10^7$–$10^8$. In contrast, small UAVs and human-powered aircraft often live in the range:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\mathrm{Re} \sim 10^5 \text{ to } 10^6
$$
</div>

<p>At these low Reynolds numbers:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Laminar boundary layers dominate</li>
  <li>Separation bubbles are common</li>
  <li>Small geometry changes can have large aerodynamic consequences</li>
</ul>

<p>XFOIL’s coupled <strong>inviscid panel method + boundary-layer solver</strong> is specifically designed to capture these effects efficiently.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="from-geometry-to-aerodynamic-coefficients">From Geometry to Aerodynamic Coefficients</h2>

<p>Given an airfoil shape, XFOIL solves for the pressure distribution and boundary-layer state around the perimeter, producing integrated aerodynamic coefficients:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Lift coefficient $C_l$</li>
  <li>Drag coefficient $C_d$</li>
  <li>Moment coefficient $C_m$</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251221/fig-xfoilcap.png" alt="XFOIL Results" />
<em>XFOIL solution showing pressure coefficient and boundary-layer state around the airfoil, along with resulting aerodynamic coefficients.</em></p>

<p>The lift coefficient is defined as:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
C_l = \frac{L}{\tfrac{1}{2} \rho U^2 S}
$$
</div>

<p>This normalization allows results to be compared across scales, speeds, and densities — critical when extrapolating between test cases.</p>

<p>XFOIL allows these coefficients to be computed across:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Angle of attack sweeps</li>
  <li>Reynolds number sweeps</li>
  <li>Different boundary-layer transition assumptions</li>
</ul>

<p>That makes it ideal for mapping the <strong>operating envelope</strong> of an airfoil before committing to a wing design.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="circulation-the-quantity-that-really-matters">Circulation: The Quantity That Really Matters</h2>

<p>While lift coefficients are convenient, the deeper physical quantity behind lift is <strong>circulation</strong>.</p>

<p>For a 2D airfoil, lift per unit span is related to circulation $ \Gamma $ via the Kutta–Joukowski theorem:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
L' = \rho U \Gamma
$$
</div>

<p>Circulation provides a direct link between:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Pressure distribution</li>
  <li>Vorticity in the flow</li>
  <li>Lift generation</li>
</ul>

<p>This becomes especially important when moving from <strong>2D airfoils</strong> to <strong>3D wings</strong>, where the <em>spanwise distribution</em> of circulation determines induced drag and overall efficiency.</p>

<p>XFOIL provides the sectional lift data needed to build that circulation distribution across a wing.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="from-2d-airfoils-to-a-3d-wing">From 2D Airfoils to a 3D Wing</h2>

<p>A real wing is not a single airfoil — it is a <strong>spanwise distribution</strong> of airfoil sections, chord lengths, and twist angles.</p>

<p>For my designs, I use XFOIL to:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Analyze candidate airfoils at local Reynolds numbers</li>
  <li>Select sections that perform well across the expected lift range</li>
  <li>Assign twist to shape the spanwise lift distribution</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251221/fig-2.png" alt="Wing Planform" />
<em>Planform layout showing spanwise airfoil sections and geometric twist distribution.</em></p>

<p>The goal is simple in principle:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Maximize lift for a given power</li>
  <li>Minimize drag, especially induced drag</li>
  <li>Maintain gentle stall behavior</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="induced-drag-and-lift-distribution">Induced Drag and Lift Distribution</h2>

<p>For a finite wing, induced drag arises from trailing vortices and depends on how lift is distributed along the span.</p>

<p>In coefficient form, induced drag can be written as:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
C_{D_i} = \frac{C_L^2}{\pi e \, \mathrm{AR}}
$$
</div>

<p>where:</p>
<ul>
  <li>$ C_L $ is the wing lift coefficient</li>
  <li>$ \mathrm{AR} $ is aspect ratio</li>
  <li>$ e $ is the span efficiency factor</li>
</ul>

<p>The efficiency factor $e$ encodes how close the actual lift distribution is to the ideal elliptical case.</p>

<div class="math-boundary"> $$ \Gamma(\theta)=2 b U_\infty \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} A_n \sin(n\theta), \qquad y=\frac{b}{2}\cos\theta,\ \theta\in[0,\pi] $$ </div>

<p>then the induced drag factor comes out:</p>

<div class="math-boundary"> $$ e=\frac{1}{1+\sum_{n=2}^{\infty} n\left(\frac{A_n}{A_1}\right)^2} $$ </div>

<div class="math-boundary"> $$ C_L=\pi\,AR\,A_1, \qquad C_{D_i}=\pi\,AR\sum_{n=1}^{\infty} n A_n^2 $$ </div>

<p>By shaping the spanwise circulation — through twist, taper, and airfoil selection — induced drag can be reduced significantly. XFOIL provides the sectional data needed to make those design decisions quantitatively rather than by intuition alone.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-this-workflow-works">Why This Workflow Works</h2>

<p>XFOIL is not a replacement for CFD or experiments. Instead, it plays a very specific and valuable role:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It is fast enough for <strong>design iteration</strong></li>
  <li>It captures key low-Reynolds-number physics</li>
  <li>It produces interpretable aerodynamic quantities</li>
  <li>It enables informed 3D wing design before expensive analysis</li>
</ul>

<p>For both my UAV work and my human-powered aircraft project, XFOIL is the tool that lets me move confidently from a sketch of an airfoil to a wing that has a realistic chance of working in the real world.</p>

<p>Everything downstream — lifting-line models, BEM codes, CFD, and eventually flight testing — depends on getting this first step right.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="CAE" /><category term="Drone" /><category term="Fixed Wing" /><category term="Aerodynamics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Using XFOIL to bridge the gap between airfoil geometry and aerodynamic performance at low Reynolds number.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD Thesis: Afterburner Flame Dynamics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/afterburner_thesis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Thesis: Afterburner Flame Dynamics" /><published>2025-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/afterburner_thesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/afterburner_thesis.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-afterburners-are-hard">Why Afterburners Are Hard</h2>
<p>Afterburners live in a difficult corner of fluid mechanics: high-speed turbulent flow, intense heat release, strong recirculation, and unsteady pressure coupling. A flameholder has to do two contradictory things at once:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Create a stable recirculation zone to anchor a flame</li>
  <li>Do as little damage as possible to pressure recovery and thrust</li>
</ul>

<p>For vee-gutter bluff-body flameholders, stability comes from the wake. Hot combustion products recirculate behind the gutter, ignite incoming reactants, and sustain a flame even when residence times are extremely short. The same wake, however, is inherently unsteady and sheds vortices that can couple to acoustics and lead to thermoacoustic instabilities.</p>

<p>Understanding <em>how</em> that wake behaves — and whether simulations reproduce it for the right reasons — was the central motivation of my PhD.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-my-thesis-set-out-to-do">What My Thesis Set Out to Do</h2>

<p>Most combustion simulations are “validated” using time-averaged quantities: mean velocities, RMS fluctuations, or single-point spectra. Those metrics are necessary, but they are not sufficient for unsteady reacting flows.</p>

<p>This work asked a more demanding question:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Can we validate simulations based on the <em>structure and dynamics</em> of the dominant flow and heat-release modes?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To answer that, I designed and built a dedicated afterburner-scale experiment and paired it with Large Eddy Simulations (LES). Proper Orthogonal Decomposition (POD) was then used as the common language between experiment and computation.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-experimental-rig">The Experimental Rig</h2>

<p>The experimental setup was built from scratch in the Combustion Systems Dynamics Lab at Virginia Tech. It consisted of:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A modular fuel-injection section</li>
  <li>A long converging section to control boundary-layer development</li>
  <li>A rectangular test section with optical access</li>
  <li>A 70° vee-gutter flameholder spanning the duct</li>
</ul>

<p>High-speed diagnostics included:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Stereo Particle Image Velocimetry (PIV)</strong> for velocity fields</li>
  <li><strong>Filtered chemiluminescence imaging</strong> as a proxy for heat release</li>
</ul>

<p>The rig was designed to operate in both non-reacting (cold-flow) and reacting regimes, allowing a controlled progression from pure fluid mechanics to fully coupled combustion dynamics.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="large-eddy-simulation">Large Eddy Simulation</h2>

<p>On the computational side, LES models were developed in both <strong>ANSYS Fluent</strong> and <strong>OpenFOAM</strong>, matched as closely as possible to the experiment.</p>

<p>At the heart of LES is a spatial filtering of the Navier–Stokes equations:</p>
<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\frac{\partial \bar{\rho}}{\partial t} + \nabla \cdot (\bar{\rho} \tilde{\mathbf{u}}) = 0
$$
</div>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\frac{\partial \bar{\rho} \tilde{\mathbf{u}}}{\partial t} + \nabla \cdot (\bar{\rho} \tilde{\mathbf{u}} \tilde{\mathbf{u}}) = -\nabla \bar{p} + \nabla \cdot (\bar{\tau} + \tau_{\text{sgs}})
$$
</div>

<p>Unresolved turbulence was modeled using dynamic Smagorinsky-type closures, with grid resolution chosen so that the majority of turbulent kinetic energy was resolved rather than modeled.</p>

<p>A key validation criterion was the <strong>Pope criterion</strong>, ensuring that modeled subgrid energy remained a small fraction of the resolved energy:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
M = \frac{k_{\text{sgs}}}{k_{\text{resolved}}} \lesssim 0.2
$$
</div>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251222/fig-1.png" alt="Large Eddy Simulation" />
<em>Instantaneous LES velocity magnitude showing alternating vortex shedding</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="proper-orthogonal-decomposition-pod">Proper Orthogonal Decomposition (POD)</h2>

<p>POD provided the bridge between experiment and simulation.</p>

<p>Given a set of instantaneous snapshots assembled into a data matrix $ \mathbf{U} $, POD seeks a low-dimensional representation:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\mathbf{U} \approx \sum_{i=1}^N a_i(t) \, \boldsymbol{\phi}_i(\mathbf{x})
$$
</div>

<div>

  <p>where:</p>

  <ul>
    <li>$ \boldsymbol{\phi}_i $ are spatial modes</li>
    <li>$ a_i(t) $     are temporal coefficients</li>
    <li>Each mode represents a coherent physical structure</li>
  </ul>

</div>

<p>Crucially, POD is agnostic to data source. Experimental measurements and LES fields can be decomposed and compared mode-by-mode.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="cold-flow-wake-dynamics">Cold Flow: Wake Dynamics</h2>

<p>In the non-reacting case, POD isolated the dominant vortex-shedding mode of the vee-gutter wake. The shedding frequency collapsed to a Strouhal number of approximately:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\mathrm{St} = \frac{f w}{U} \approx 0.24
$$
</div>

<p>The first POD modes from PIV, Fluent, and OpenFOAM showed strong agreement in:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Spatial structure</li>
  <li>Amplitude</li>
  <li>Streamwise evolution</li>
</ul>

<p>This went well beyond matching mean velocity profiles and demonstrated that the simulations were capturing the <em>right physics</em> of the wake.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251222/fig-2.png" alt="Cold Wake" />
<em>POD modes of the cold flow PIV data (top row) and CFD simulations (Fluent middle OpenFOAM bottom)</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="reacting-flow-heat-release-dynamics">Reacting Flow: Heat Release Dynamics</h2>

<p>For reacting cases, validation became more subtle. Chemiluminescence measurements are line-of-sight integrals, while LES produces local volumetric heat release.</p>

<p>To make the comparison meaningful, the LES heat release was integrated numerically along synthetic lines of sight:</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251222/fig4-flameprojection.png" alt="Hot Wake" />
<em>Instantaneous heat flame sheet left with integrated heat release “image” on the left</em>
fig4-flameprojection.png</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
I(x,y) = \int \dot{q}^{'''}(x,y,z) \, dz
$$
</div>

<video controls="" autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="" style="max-width:100%;">
  <source src="assets/img/posts/20251222/flameprojection.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<p><em>Animation of the simulated flame (left) and the integrated heat release image $I(x,y)$ on the right</em></p>

<p>POD of these integrated fields revealed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A dominant symmetric shedding mode</li>
  <li>Higher-frequency harmonic modes</li>
  <li>A low-frequency, low-energy mode invisible to time-averaged analysis</li>
</ul>

<p>The agreement in mode shape, frequency, and relative energy between experiment and LES provided strong evidence that the simulations were dynamically faithful.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251222/fig-3.png" alt="Hot Wake" />
<em>POD modes of the heat release chemiluminescence data (left) and CFD simulation in Fluent (right)</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h2>

<p>The most important outcome of this work was methodological.</p>

<p>By validating <strong>dynamic modes</strong>, not just statistics, we gain confidence that LES models can be trusted to explore:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Confinement effects</li>
  <li>Boundary condition sensitivity</li>
  <li>Transitions between symmetric and asymmetric flame dynamics</li>
</ul>

<p>This is essential for predicting combustion instability risk, flameholder performance, and operability limits in real engines.</p>

<h2 id="so-what">So What?</h2>

<p>My PhD sat deliberately at the intersection of <strong>design, experiment, simulation, and data-driven analysis</strong>. Building the hardware mattered. Writing the solvers mattered. But the real leverage came from learning how to ask better validation questions.</p>

<p>That mindset — validating <em>structure</em>, not just numbers — continues to shape how I approach complex engineering problems today.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="Dynamics" /><category term="Experiment" /><category term="Combustion" /><category term="Afterburner" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Designing, building, and validating an afterburner flameholder experiment using LES and Proper Orthogonal Decomposition.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing a Human-Powered Aircraft</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/human_powered_airplane.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing a Human-Powered Aircraft" /><published>2025-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/human_powered_airplane</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/human_powered_airplane.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-childhood-idea-that-never-went-away">A Childhood Idea That Never Went Away</h2>

<p>Some engineering projects start with a problem statement.<br />
This one started with a PBS documentary.</p>

<p>I was a kid when I first saw a program about the <strong>Daedalus Project</strong>, the human-powered aircraft that successfully flew from Crete to Santorini. I don’t remember all the details, but I <em>do</em> remember what it did to my imagination. Suddenly, flying didn’t feel like something reserved for jet engines and control towers — it felt almost personal. Human. Attainable.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4pbKp7ufwns" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Not long after, I started sketching designs for a human-powered helicopter that my friends and I could pedal up into the nearby mountains for a camping trip. Needless to say, the physics were… optimistic.</p>

<p>Around the same time, a PBS science show flashed an equation on the screen:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
F_L = \tfrac{1}{2}\rho U^2 C_L A
$$
</div>

<p>I remember scrambling to find out when the episode would re-air so I could be ready with pen and paper. I copied it down, stared at it, and immediately realized I was in way over my head. I didn’t know what density was. I definitely didn’t know how anyone could possibly determine $C_L$.</p>

<p>But that equation stuck.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="coming-back-with-better-tools">Coming Back With Better Tools</h2>

<p>Decades later, that same equation still sits at the heart of this project — but now it’s surrounded by tools I didn’t have back then.</p>

<p>Designing a human-powered aircraft is a brutally constrained problem:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Very low available power</strong> (on the order of 200–300 W sustained)</li>
  <li><strong>Very low flight speeds</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Extremely low Reynolds numbers</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Severe mass and structural constraints</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Every design decision is coupled. Wing area drives drag. Drag drives power. Power caps speed. Speed feeds directly back into lift.</p>

<p>The basic lift requirement is still simple:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
L = W
$$
</div>

<p>But achieving that lift efficiently at walking-to-jogging speeds is anything but.</p>

<p>This project is where all of the threads from earlier posts come together:<br />
airfoil analysis with <strong>XFOIL</strong>, wing design and induced drag management, propeller optimization for static and low-speed thrust, and an unapologetically iterative design-build mindset.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-configuration">The Configuration</h2>

<p>The current concept is a <strong>tractor configuration</strong> with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A very high aspect ratio wing</li>
  <li>Carefully managed twist distribution</li>
  <li>A lightweight fuselage nacelle just large enough for the pilot and drivetrain</li>
  <li>A propeller optimized specifically for low-speed efficiency</li>
</ul>

<p>The aircraft is designed around <em>the pilot</em>, not the other way around. The seating position, drivetrain geometry, and center of gravity placement are all chosen to minimize trim drag and structural penalties.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20260123/fig1_iso.png" alt="Isometric view of the human-powered aircraft" />
<em>Isometric CAD rendering showing overall configuration and pilot integration</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="designing-for-low-reynolds-number-flight">Designing for Low Reynolds Number Flight</h2>

<p>At the speeds a human can realistically sustain, Reynolds numbers are typically an order of magnitude lower than conventional aircraft. That changes everything:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\mathrm{Re} = \frac{\rho U c}{\mu}
$$
</div>

<p>At low Reynolds numbers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Laminar separation becomes a dominant concern</li>
  <li>Small changes in airfoil geometry have outsized effects</li>
  <li>Empirical intuition from conventional aircraft breaks down</li>
</ul>

<p>This is why tools like <strong>XFOIL</strong> are indispensable. They allow me to go from <em>geometry</em> to <em>aerodynamic performance</em> and close the loop between concept and reality.</p>

<p>But airfoils are only half the story.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="wing-planform-and-structural-reality">Wing Planform and Structural Reality</h2>

<p>The wing planform is driven by two competing goals:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Minimize induced drag through a near-elliptical lift distribution</li>
  <li>Maintain a structure that can actually be built and carried</li>
</ul>

<p>Twist is used aggressively to shape the spanwise loading while keeping root bending moments manageable. The wing is broken into discrete sections that balance aerodynamic idealism with structural pragmatism.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20260123/fig2-front.png" alt="Front view of the aircraft" />
<em>Front view highlighting extreme aspect ratio and spanwise twist</em></p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20260123/fig3-top.png" alt="Top view of the aircraft" />
<em>Top view showing planform, control surfaces, and wing segmentation</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-this-project-matters-to-me">Why This Project Matters (to Me)</h2>

<p>This isn’t about breaking records or chasing headlines.</p>

<p>It’s about finally revisiting an idea that’s been quietly present for most of my life — but doing it with the right tools, the right physics, and the right level of respect for how hard the problem actually is.</p>

<p>Every part of this aircraft exists because of something I once struggled to understand:</p>

<ul>
  <li>That mysterious lift equation</li>
  <li>Why drag matters more than you think</li>
  <li>Why efficiency is a system-level property</li>
  <li>Why building hardware teaches you things simulations never will</li>
</ul>

<p>This project sits at the intersection of <strong>curiosity, discipline, and persistence</strong> — and for me, that’s where the most meaningful engineering lives.</p>

<p>There’s still a long way to go. But for the first time, this isn’t a sketch in a notebook.</p>

<p>It’s an airplane.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="Aerospace" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Human Powered" /><category term="Fixed Wing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A lifelong idea, finally approached with real engineering tools.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Propeller Design with XFOIL and QPROP</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/xfoil_toqprop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Propeller Design with XFOIL and QPROP" /><published>2025-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/xfoil_toqprop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/xfoil_toqprop.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-propeller-design-is-hard">Why Propeller Design Is Hard</h2>

<p>A propeller is just a rotating wing — but that simple statement hides a lot of complexity.</p>

<p>Unlike a fixed wing, every blade section on a propeller:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Sees a different relative velocity</li>
  <li>Operates at a different effective angle of attack</li>
  <li>Contributes simultaneously to <strong>thrust</strong> and <strong>torque</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Designing a propeller therefore requires closing a loop between:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>2D airfoil performance</strong></li>
  <li><strong>3D blade geometry</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Integral thrust, torque, and power</strong></li>
</ol>

<p>This is where <strong>XFOIL</strong> and <strong>QPROP</strong> come in. XFOIL provides the sectional aerodynamics. QPROP integrates those sections into a rotating blade model and predicts the global performance.</p>

<p>Together, they form a fast, physics-based path from <strong>geometry → performance</strong>, which is exactly what I needed for UAV and human-powered aircraft propellers.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="theoretical-background-qprop-in-a-nutshell">Theoretical Background (QPROP in a Nutshell)</h2>

<p>QPROP is based on blade-element / momentum theory with careful accounting of velocities and induced effects. A blade element at radius $r$ sees a relative velocity composed of axial and tangential components:</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20260125/fig-qprop_theory.png" alt="QPROP Velocity Diagram" />
<em>Velocity components and force decomposition used in <a href="https://web.mit.edu/drela/Public/web/qprop/qprop_theory.pdf">QPROP blade-element theory</a></em></p>

<p>The local relative velocity magnitude is:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
W = \sqrt{(V_a + u_a)^2 + (\Omega r - u_t)^2}
$$
</div>

<p>where:</p>
<ul>
  <li>$V_a$ is axial inflow velocity</li>
  <li>$\Omega r$ is tangential blade speed</li>
  <li>$u_a, u_t$ are induced axial and tangential velocities</li>
</ul>

<p>The blade section angle of attack depends directly on the <strong>local twist angle</strong> $\beta(r)$ and the inflow angle $\phi$:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\alpha(r) = \beta(r) - \phi(r)
$$
</div>

<p>This immediately explains why <strong>twist matters</strong>, even for propellers optimized for static thrust: each radius experiences a different inflow direction, and without twist, most of the blade would operate far from its optimal lift condition.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="thrust-torque-and-power">Thrust, Torque, and Power</h2>

<p>For a blade element of chord $c(r)$, the differential thrust and torque are:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
dT = \tfrac{1}{2} \rho W^2 c \left( C_l \cos\phi - C_d \sin\phi \right) dr
$$
</div>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
dQ = r \, \tfrac{1}{2} \rho W^2 c \left( C_l \sin\phi + C_d \cos\phi \right) dr
$$
</div>

<p>Integrating along the blade yields total thrust $T$ and torque $Q$, with power given by:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
P = Q \, \Omega
$$
</div>

<p>Even in <strong>static thrust</strong> conditions ($V_a = 0$), the blade experiences a strong radial variation in inflow angle. A propeller optimized for static thrust still requires careful twist design to keep each section near its peak $C_l/C_d$.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="nomenclature-following-qprop">Nomenclature (Following QPROP)</h2>

<p>Using the notation from Drela’s formulation:</p>

<ul>
  <li>$W$ — Relative velocity magnitude</li>
  <li>$V_a$ — Axial inflow velocity</li>
  <li>$\Omega r$ — Tangential blade speed</li>
  <li>$u_a, u_t$ — Induced velocities</li>
  <li>$\phi$ — Inflow angle</li>
  <li>$\beta$ — Blade pitch (twist) angle</li>
  <li>$\alpha$ — Section angle of attack</li>
  <li>$C_l, C_d$ — Sectional lift and drag coefficients</li>
</ul>

<p>A full derivation is available in the original QPROP theory document:
<a href="https://web.mit.edu/drela/Public/web/qprop/qprop_theory.pdf">QPROP Theory PDF</a></p>

<p>QPROP itself is written and maintained by <strong>Mark Drela</strong>, whose tools have quietly shaped decades of practical aerodynamic design:
<a href="https://web.mit.edu/drela/Public/web/qprop/">web.mit.edu/drela/qprop</a></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="feeding-xfoil-into-qprop">Feeding XFOIL into QPROP</h2>

<p>QPROP does not invent airfoil aerodynamics — it consumes them.</p>

<p>For each blade section:</p>
<ol>
  <li>XFOIL is used to generate polars $(C_l, C_d, C_m)$</li>
  <li>These are fitted with quadratic functions of $C_l = f(C_d)$</li>
  <li>QPROP uses those curve fits plus Reynolds Number and Prandtl-Glauert to predict local airfoil performance</li>
</ol>

<p>So the workflow can capture the relevant physics:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Airfoil choice</li>
  <li>Reynolds number range</li>
  <li>Compressibility effects at elevate local Mach Number</li>
  <li>Transition modeling assumptions</li>
</ul>

<p>At the low Reynolds numbers relevant for small UAVs and human-powered aircraft, this coupling matters enormously.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="python-automation-and-optimization">Python Automation and Optimization</h2>

<p>While QPROP is fast, running it manually is not how you design a propeller.</p>

<p>I built a <strong>Python wrapper</strong> around QPROP that:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Generates candidate blade geometries (chord and twist parameterizations)</li>
  <li>Calls QPROP programmatically</li>
  <li>Parses thrust, torque, and power outputs</li>
  <li>Feeds results into an optimizer</li>
</ul>

<p>This allowed me to optimize directly for objectives like:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Maximum static thrust at fixed power</li>
  <li>Thrust-to-torque ratio</li>
  <li>Sensitivity to RPM variations</li>
</ul>

<p>Getting this working reliably took nontrivial effort:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Compiling legacy Fortran on macOS</li>
  <li>Dealing with compiler quirks and I/O formatting</li>
  <li>Making the wrapper robust to failed convergence cases</li>
  <li>Experimenting with different optimization algorithms</li>
</ul>

<p>It was worth it. Once automated, design iteration became fast and quantitative instead of trial-and-error.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="from-optimized-geometry-to-cad">From Optimized Geometry to CAD</h2>

<p>The final step was turning optimized blade distributions into real hardware.</p>

<p>The propeller was parameterized such that:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Each blade could be split into two printable segments</li>
  <li>A central hub could be printed separately</li>
  <li>All parts could be bonded or mechanically joined</li>
</ul>

<p>This drove constraints back into the optimization:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Minimum chord for structural integrity</li>
  <li>Twist smoothness for manufacturability</li>
  <li>Hub-root geometry compatibility</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20260125/fig-onshape_prop.png" alt="CAD Propeller" />
<em>Propeller drawn in CAD using OnShape</em></p>

<p>The result was a propeller that:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Matches the optimized aerodynamic geometry</li>
  <li>Can be manufactured with desktop tools</li>
  <li>Is suitable for static testing and iteration</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20260125/fig-printed_prop.jpeg" alt="Printed Propeller" />
<em>3D-printed propeller assembled from a central hub and two segments per blade.</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-this-workflow-matters">Why This Workflow Matters</h2>

<p>This XFOIL → QPROP → Python → CAD pipeline closes the loop from <strong>theory to hardware</strong>.</p>

<p>It allows:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Fast iteration at the concept stage</li>
  <li>Quantitative trade studies</li>
  <li>Direct connection between aerodynamic assumptions and measured performance</li>
</ul>

<p>Most importantly, it avoids over-investing in high-fidelity CFD before the fundamental design space has been explored.</p>

<p>For small aircraft, that leverage is everything.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>XFOIL and QPROP are not flashy tools. They are not new. But they encode decades of aerodynamic insight in a form that rewards careful thinking.</p>

<p>Used together — and automated properly — they form a design workflow that is fast, transparent, and grounded in physics. That combination is rare, and it’s why they remain central to how I design propellers today.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="Aerodynamics" /><category term="Propellers" /><category term="UAV" /><category term="HPA" /><category term="CAE" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Closing the loop from airfoil geometry to thrust, torque, and power using XFOIL, QPROP, and Python-driven optimization.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting a Formula SAE Team from Scratch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/formulaSAE.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting a Formula SAE Team from Scratch" /><published>2025-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/formulaSAE</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/formulaSAE.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-formula-sae-is">What Formula SAE Is</h2>

<p>Formula SAE is a student engineering competition where teams design, build, and race a small, open-wheel formula-style car. On paper it’s a motorsports competition. In reality, it’s one of the most intense systems-engineering learning environments you can experience as an undergraduate.</p>

<p>Teams are judged not just on lap time, but on:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Engineering design</li>
  <li>Manufacturing quality</li>
  <li>Cost and business case</li>
  <li>Reliability and execution</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251225/fsae_splash.png" alt="FSAE final" />
<em>The final car</em></p>

<p>Most established teams iterate year-to-year, refining designs using previous cars as testbeds. That luxury mattered a lot to us — because we didn’t have it.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="one-f1-obsession-and-one-physics-brain">One F1 Obsession and One Physics Brain</h2>

<p>The project started with a friend of mine who was, in the best possible way, an F1 obsessive. He didn’t just <em>watch</em> Formula 1 — he lived it. Telemetry, suspension geometry, aero trade studies, team politics. All of it.</p>

<p>I came from a different angle. I loved the physics: fluid flow, dynamics, structures, control. Formula SAE immediately struck me as the ultimate forcing function — a way to turn abstract coursework into something brutally real.</p>

<p>Together, we convinced our university to approve Formula SAE as a senior capstone project. That approval came with a modest budget and, more importantly, legitimacy. By the end, about <strong>20 undergraduate students</strong> were involved in designing, building, testing, and driving the car.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-lens-for-learning">A Lens for Learning</h2>

<p>I easily spent <strong>twice as much time on Formula SAE as on all my coursework combined</strong> — and it paid off in ways no class ever could.</p>

<p>Every new concept suddenly mattered:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Fluid flow → intake and cooling</li>
  <li>System dynamics → suspension and driveline</li>
  <li>CAD → everything</li>
  <li>Design for manufacturing → everything again</li>
  <li>Kinematics → suspension geometry</li>
  <li>Instrumentation → testing and debugging</li>
  <li>Statistics → data interpretation</li>
  <li>FEA and CFD → structural and aero intuition</li>
  <li>Optimization → tradeoffs everywhere</li>
</ul>

<p>Formula SAE gave me a <em>lens</em>. Instead of learning topics in isolation, every lecture felt like it could help make a better race car.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="cad-first-simulation-later-if-ever">CAD First, Simulation Later (If Ever)</h2>

<p>We realized very quickly that <strong>CAD was non-negotiable</strong>. Everything had to fit. Everything interacted. Everything had consequences.</p>

<p>The car’s structure was designed entirely by students, balancing stiffness, mass, manufacturability, and safety.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251225/fsae_CADjpg.jpg" alt="FSAE CAD Rendering" />
<em>Early CAD rendering of the Formula SAE car, showing chassis layout, suspension geometry, and packaging constraints</em></p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251225/fsae_CAD2.jpg" alt="FSAE CAD Rendering" />
<em>Refined CAD model incorporating lessons learned from the prototype build and early testing</em></p>

<p>We used finite element analysis selectively — not to chase perfect stress predictions, but to identify load paths, calculate stiffnesses, and filter out bad design concepts.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251225/FSAE_FEA.png" alt="FSAE FEA" />
<em>Finite element analysis of critical subframe sections used to guide structural reinforcement and weight reduction</em></p>

<p>Simulation was a guide, not a crutch.</p>

<hr />

<p>What we <em>couldn’t</em> do — at least not well — was simulate the full system. About 90% of the teams we competed against had previous cars to validate models against. We had nothing.</p>

<p>So we made a counterintuitive decision.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="two-cars-not-one">Two Cars, Not One</h2>

<p>Instead of betting everything on a single “perfect” design, we committed to building <strong>two cars</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A rough prototype car</li>
  <li>A refined final competition car</li>
</ul>

<p>We started in <strong>September</strong> and set an aggressive internal deadline:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>The first car would drive under its own power by January 1.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We missed that deadline by three days — but on <strong>January 4</strong>, the prototype rolled under its own power.</p>

<video controls="" autoplay="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="" style="max-width:100%;">
  <source src="assets/img/posts/20251225/tirewarmer.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<p><em>Well, more than rolled</em></p>

<p>That moment changed everything. Suddenly we had:</p>
<ul>
  <li>A testbed</li>
  <li>Real data</li>
  <li>Real failures</li>
  <li>Real intuition</li>
</ul>

<p>Everything we learned went directly into the final car.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="driving-the-thing">Driving the Thing</h2>

<p>I only drove the car once.</p>

<p>It was… <strong>violent</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>0–100 km/h in about <strong>3 seconds</strong></li>
  <li>More than <strong>1 g lateral acceleration</strong></li>
  <li>The driver wasn’t so much <em>sitting</em> as <em>lying down</em> to keep the center of gravity low</li>
  <li>My shoulders were a few centimeters from the exhaust headers</li>
</ul>

<p>They were red for days afterward.</p>

<p>It was raw, loud, uncomfortable, and absolutely unforgettable.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="results-and-trajectories">Results and Trajectories</h2>

<p>That year, we won <strong>Formula SAE Rookie of the Year</strong>.</p>

<p>But the bigger outcome was personal trajectory.</p>

<ul>
  <li>My friend went on to work for several F1 teams over the years (another story for another day)</li>
  <li>I went to graduate school to learn combustion and how to design real experiments</li>
</ul>

<p>For me, Formula SAE permanently set the direction:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>taking ideas from my head,<br />
turning them into models and mockups,<br />
and then building hardware that actually works</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-it-still-matters">Why It Still Matters</h2>

<p>That project taught me something I still rely on today:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You don’t learn engineering by avoiding complexity.<br />
You learn it by confronting complexity early, imperfectly, and honestly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Formula SAE wasn’t just a car.<br />
It was the moment engineering stopped being theoretical for me — and started being real.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="Motorsport" /><category term="Design" /><category term="CAD" /><category term="FEA" /><category term="Systems Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How building a Formula SAE car from nothing shaped how I think about engineering, design, and learning by doing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Autonomous Robot Design Competition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/autonomous_robot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Autonomous Robot Design Competition" /><published>2025-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/autonomous_robot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/autonomous_robot.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-graduate-course-disguised-as-a-trial-by-fire">A Graduate Course Disguised as a Trial by Fire</h2>

<p>As an undergraduate, my university allowed students to take up to three graduate-level courses as electives. For my first, I chose <strong>Mechatronics</strong> — partly because it sounded intimidating, and partly because I suspected it would force me to learn things I didn’t yet know I needed.</p>

<p>The course itself was largely conceptual. The <em>real</em> grade came from a semester-long group project: build an autonomous robot capable of navigating a complex course and completing a multi-object task under uncertainty.</p>

<p>I was grouped with two PhD students. Both were racing to finish and defend their dissertations that same semester.</p>

<p>Which meant — very quickly — that a large fraction of the project landed on me.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251223/turtle.jpg" alt="First design iteration of Turtle" />
<em>The final product of much sweat and many tears - “the Turtle”</em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-challenge-turtles-world">The Challenge: Turtle’s World</h2>

<p>The robot (eventually named <strong>Turtle</strong>) had to autonomously navigate a course featuring:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ramps and uneven terrain</li>
  <li>A bridge with <strong>transparent decking</strong></li>
  <li>Multicolored walls and boundary regions</li>
  <li>A “soccer goal”</li>
  <li>Multiple <strong>multicolored ping pong balls</strong>, only some of which were valid targets</li>
</ul>

<p>Points were awarded for:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Completing the full course</li>
  <li>Capturing the <em>correct</em> color balls</li>
  <li>Returning them to the goal</li>
</ul>

<p>Points were deducted for grabbing the wrong balls.</p>

<p>No teleoperation. No resets.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-hardware-we-had-and-didnt">The Hardware We Had (and Didn’t)</h2>

<p>Our available hardware was minimal and unforgiving:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A few <strong>DC motors</strong> and <strong>servo motors</strong></li>
  <li>A <strong>CMUcam</strong> (RS-232 color vision camera)</li>
  <li>An ultrasonic rangefinder</li>
  <li>An embedded controller with limited ADC and PWM</li>
  <li>Batteries, wires, and <em>lots</em> of LEGO</li>
  <li>Whatever mechanical parts we could scrounge</li>
</ul>

<p>No encoders. No IMU. No real odometry.</p>

<p>Just enough rope to hang ourselves.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="team-roles-and-reality">Team Roles (and Reality)</h2>

<p>Despite the pressure, the team dynamic worked remarkably well:</p>

<ul>
  <li>One teammate was strong in <strong>software</strong></li>
  <li>One was skilled with <strong>electronics</strong></li>
  <li>I became:
    <ul>
      <li>Mechanical designer</li>
      <li>Systems integrator</li>
      <li>Algorithm developer</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I also became the person who had to decide which ambitious ideas to kill <em>early</em>.</p>

<p>Because it became clear very quickly:<br />
<strong>Even with years, this problem would be hard.</strong></p>

<p>We had months.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="mistakes-so-many-mistakes">Mistakes (So Many Mistakes)</h2>

<p>We made nearly every mistake you can make on a first autonomous system:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Trusted <strong>open-loop wheel control</strong> far too long</li>
  <li>Assumed the CMUcam’s color thresholds wouldn’t drift when someone opened a window</li>
  <li>Mounted batteries so high that we lost traction on steep ramps</li>
  <li>Tried to do “precision” navigation with no real state estimation</li>
  <li>Underestimated how fast perception degrades as speed increases</li>
</ul>

<p>Every subsystem interfered with every other subsystem.</p>

<p>Raising the camera improved visibility but raised the center of gravity.<br />
Driving faster improved coverage but destroyed perception reliability.<br />
Adding batteries improved run time but made ramps impossible.</p>

<p>It was systems engineering, whether we liked it or not.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-night-everything-changed">The Night Everything Changed</h2>

<p>About halfway through the semester, I was alone in the lab one evening, staring at camera data and motor commands, when something clicked.</p>

<p>We didn’t need precision.</p>

<p>We needed <strong>feedback</strong>.</p>

<p>Using the CMUcam, we could compute the <strong>horizontal offset of a ball’s image centroid</strong> from the center of the camera’s field of view. That offset could be treated as an error signal.</p>

<p>So I implemented a simple <strong>P-controller</strong>:</p>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
e = x_{\text{ball}} - x_{\text{center}}
$$
</div>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\omega_L = \omega_0 - K_p e
$$
</div>

<div class="math-boundary">
$$
\omega_R = \omega_0 + K_p e
$$
</div>

<p>That was it. No integral. No derivative. Just proportional feedback.</p>

<p>The robot <em>homed in</em> on the ball.</p>

<p>Once the image centroid dropped low enough in the frame (meaning the ball was close), we switched to open-loop forward motion and trapped the ball between the front wheels.</p>

<p>It worked.</p>

<p>The feeling when it worked the first time — and when I showed it to my teammates the next day and it worked <em>again</em> — was unforgettable.</p>

<p>That was the moment feedback control stopped being math and became behavior.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="iterating-the-design---the-mouse-and-the-brick">Iterating the Design - the Mouse and the Brick</h2>

<p>We went through <strong>three major design phases</strong> over the semester, each one informed by painful lessons from the previous.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251223/Robot_1st_Draft_pic_2.JPG" alt="First design iteration of Turtle" />
<em>First design iteration: ambitious, unstable, and far too optimistic, “the Mouse”</em></p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251223/Robot_2nd_Draft_pic_2.JPG" alt="Second design iteration of Turtle" />
<em>Second iteration: lower center of gravity, improved camera placement, and simplified mechanisms, lovingly referred to as “the Brick”</em></p>

<p>Each iteration stripped away complexity and increased robustness.</p>

<p>By the end of the semester, our robot was the <strong>only one</strong> that could reliably navigate the course — and the only one that could capture balls.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-almost-perfect-run">The Almost-Perfect Run</h2>

<p>We completed the course.<br />
We captured all the balls.</p>

<p>But we missed a perfect score.</p>

<p>We never had time to implement a proper <strong>ball ejector</strong>. Instead, we relied on a servo-actuated flap and an open-loop “charge the goal and brake” maneuver.</p>

<p>The balls got stuck on the chassis.</p>

<p>So close.</p>

<p>Only afterward did the professor admit that this was the <strong>fourth year</strong> he had taught the course that way — and that no team had ever completed the full challenge.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-turtle-still-matters-to-me">Why Turtle Still Matters to Me</h2>

<p>This project cost me an enormous amount of time. Easily more than all my other coursework combined that semester.</p>

<p>And it was absolutely worth it.</p>

<p>It taught me:</p>

<ul>
  <li>That feedback beats precision</li>
  <li>That hardware lies</li>
  <li>That perception and control are inseparable</li>
  <li>That simple equations can produce lifelike behavior</li>
  <li>That open-ended problems are where real learning happens</li>
</ul>

<p>Most importantly, it set my trajectory.</p>

<p>This was the first time I took something messy, underdefined, and borderline impossible — and made it work through iteration, physics, and stubbornness.</p>

<p>Turtle didn’t just navigate a course.</p>

<p>It taught me how to engineer.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="Robotics" /><category term="Control" /><category term="Mechatronics" /><category term="Systems" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An autonomous robot, a graduate-level course, and my first real encounter with feedback control.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixed Wing UAV Aero+Structural Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/droneCADCFD.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixed Wing UAV Aero+Structural Design" /><published>2025-11-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/droneCADCFD</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/droneCADCFD.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Coming Soon</strong>
<img src="assets/img/posts/20251226/splash.png" alt="CFD Drone" />
<em>CFD for Drone Design</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="opinion" /><category term="CAD" /><category term="CFD" /><category term="drone" /><category term="fixed wing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CFD for Drone Design]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CFD-based Constrained Optimization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CFD_based_optimization.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CFD-based Constrained Optimization" /><published>2025-11-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CFD_based_optimization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CFD_based_optimization.html"><![CDATA[<p>** Coming Soon**</p>

<p>CFD-based Optimization is potentially incredibly powerful but creates all sorts of interactions between numerical methods that limits its applicability, this is an study on how to overcome some of those problems.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251224/gradients.png" alt="Gradient Based Optimization with CFD" /></p>

<p><em>CFD for optimization requires understanding how numerical methods interact and how to design a study that won’t game itself</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="opinion" /><category term="CFD" /><category term="optimization" /><category term="sensitivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CFD for optimization requires understanding how numerical methods interact and how to design a study that won't game itself]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Human Mechanical Power Simulation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bike_power_data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Human Mechanical Power Simulation" /><published>2025-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/bike_power_data</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bike_power_data.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Coming Soon</strong>
I have developed tools for simulating how my heart responds when I generate different amounts of mechanical power as I pedal my bike …. AND crucially, how all that changes as I get more (or less) fit over the course of a cycling season.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/posts/20251220/bikepowerdata.png" alt="Bike Power and Speed" />
<em>Simulated and measured power, speed, and heart rate for a bike ride in North Carolina</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Blanchard</name></author><category term="opinion" /><category term="data" /><category term="cycling" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As neural networks are used more and more in the creative process, text, images and even music are now created by AI, but who owns the copyright for those works?]]></summary></entry></feed>